诸神字幕组 www.kamigami.org
日听：NEKO 翻译&校对：小卷 压制&发布：娜夏大人
Studio Rikka
In the future, probably Japan.
“Robots” have seen practical use for some time.
This is an era just after the widespread deployment of “Androids.”
We’ve identified the information source.
情報発信源を特定しました
As expected, it’s from the same district.
やはり同じ地区です
This time it was transmitted via more than five other androids.
今回は五体以上のアンドロイドを経由しています
Somehow, the pattern diverged.
パターン 分岐しました
Just as we tho—
尚　やは…
Trace the recipient unit.
受信画だけをトレースして
Recipient identified.
受信機体　特定しました
I’ve found it on my end as well.
こちらでもモニターした
I’m surprised.
驚いた
That is Shiotsuki’s parting gift, isn’t it?
この機体　潮月の置き土産ね
と言いますと?
What are you trying to say?
Shiotsuki’s ai, Code:life—do you recall that implementation experiment?
潮月のAI－code:LIFE の実装実験　覚えてる?
The one that you forcefully halted?
主任が強制停止したあれですか
I didn’t know it had been continued.
再稼動中とは知りませんでした
And externally, too.
それも施設外で
All related personnel are under protective observation.
関係職員宅にて保護観察中
It’s all connected in ways I had not foreseen.
思わぬところで繋がったよね
In any case,
いずれにせよ　この地区一帯のアンドロイドがあの店の情報を得ているのはほぼ確定
it’s almost certain that the androids in this district are receiving messages from that café.
And all via communication among their own kind.
しかも彼ら同士の会話で
Is this your doing as well, Shiotsuki?
潮月　これもあなたの仕業なの
Now tracing the location of the unit in question.
該当機体の現在位置　トレース開始します
Time of EVE
ログは正常に書き出されました　マスター
The log has been successfully written, Master.
Question.
質問
何でしょうか
What is it?
いや…
Well …
質問キャンセル
Cancel question.
コーヒー
Coffee.
Acknowledged.
かしこまりました
みんなは…じゃなくて
Where is—I mean,
ステータス:家族
Status: Family.
Your father has taken up residence at his workplace.
お父様は仕事場に宿泊されています
お母様は私の復帰時刻よりもはやくお出かけになりました
Your mother left before my activation.
I believe Naoko-sama is still in bed.
ナオコ様はまだ就寝中と思われます
帰宅時間
Time of return.
3:18 a.m.
午前3時18分です
ああ　気持ち悪い
I feel terrible.
Then you shouldn’t have gone drinking.
なら飲まなきゃいいじゃん
It felt good at first.
最初は気持ちいいの
Order your own coffee!
自分で頼んでよコーヒー
飲み会のあとさ　迎えに来たのよこれ
After the party, this thing came to pick me up.
I was so embarrassed.
めちゃくちゃ恥ずかしかったんだけど
朝食はいかがいたしますか
What about breakfast?
Cancel breakfast.
朝食キャンセル
I am really sorry.
申し訳ありません　もう一度お願いします
Could you please repeat—
One serving of breakfast immediately.
朝食一人分　今すぐ
かしこまりました
Acknowledged.
日本国内における食料自給率が8割を超えたことが明らかになりました
Our domestic food self-sufficiency ratio will soon exceed 80%.
Domestic food self-sufficiency ratio exceeds 80%
Agricultural Ministry
The biggest pace of expansion since robot
labor was introduced into primary industries.
This is the finding from an investigation by the Agricultural Ministry—
これは食料管理省の調べによ…
Would you eat a tomato created by machines?
In such an age, treasure warmth.
Ethics Committee
Whoa! In other words, “dori-kei” refers to a psychological dependence on androids, yes?
つまりドリ系とは　アンドロイド精神依存症からきているんですねですね
Recently, this is what young people who treat house-roids as humans are being called.
最近では　ハウスロイドを人間視してしまう若者をこう呼ぶんですけれども
We bring you our investigation of these “dori-kei” people.
そんなドリ系と呼ばれる人たちを取材しました
Ah, how gross! They should just like … clear off.
きもい　どっか行ってって感じ
They were all arm-in-arm and stuff.
なんか腕組んで…
Whoa, that’s intense!
きつっ
Isn’t it just loneliness? Like if they don’t have any friends …
寂しいんじゃないの　友達とかもいなくて
You should be careful too.
あんたも気付けてよね
What do you mean by that?
気付けてってなんだよ
… Just order it around.
Rikuo. I saw your sister yesterday.
リクオ
昨日お前の姉ちゃん見たぞ
Midnight, right?
夜中でしょう
At the station turnstiles. She was pretty drunk.
改札で　かなり酔ってた
She was properly escorted.
ちゃんと迎えに行ったって
You went?
お前が?
Our android did.
ちのアンドロイド
Like I said …
だからさ…
お前はロボット信用しすぎだつーの
You trust robots way too much.
It’s not really a matter of trust.
別に信用してるわけじゃないけどさ
ほらなんとか原則
Come on. The whatever laws.
The three laws of robotics.
ロボット三原則
First Law.
第一条
Do not inflict injury on humans. Protect humans.
人間に危害を加えない　人間を守る
Oh. Is that why it went to pick her up?
それで迎えに行ったのか
It’s not like they worry about humans.
人間を心配してるわけじゃねぇんだ
持ってんならその辺考えろよ
You have an android;
at least think about these things.
You’re one to talk. You don’t even have one.
持ってない奴がよく言うよ
ね　これどう思う
Hey, what do you think about this?
It’s a bunch of numbers.
数字が並んでる
These are movement records for my android.
行動記録
うちのアンドロイドの
Which part?
どの辺が?
Are you free after this?
このあと暇?
I want you to come with me.
ちょっと付き合ってほしいんだけど
どこに
Where to?
That’s … I don’t know.
それが…分かんない
What’s up with that?
なんだそれ
It has been acting strange recently, coming home at weird hours.
最近様子が変でさ　帰宅時間がばらついてたり
Your robot?
お前んちのロボット?
So I got concerned and looked into its movement records.
それで気になって調べたんだよ行動記録
そしたら
And …?
Twenty hours ago; that’d be yesterday afternoon?
20時間前だから
昨日の昼過ぎかな
It went off on its own.
勝手に寄り道してた
That’s because … it had things to do, right?
そりゃ…
用事があったんだろう
Here?
ここで?
Here? Seriously?
You’re lost
マジでここ?
I wonder if the gps’s calibration is off?
GPSずれてるのかな
This isn’t a place that robots would come to.
ロボットが来る場所じゃねぇだろう
おい
Hey.
怪しくね?
Doesn’t it seem suspicious?
If we don’t go in …
そりゃ入ってみないと
怪しいかな
It is kinda suspicious.
Then should we go home?
じゃ帰るか
Time of Eve’s Rule
In this café,
there is to be no discrimination
between humans and robots.
Customers, please cooperate
Obey the rule and have a fun time... Nagi
これって
This is—
Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ
空いてる席にどうぞ
Please take any seat that’s free.
I’ll take your orders soon.
注文取りに行くから
はい　そっちね
Right. Over there, yeah?
It might only be a short while,
短い時間かもしれないけど
but enjoy yourselves, all right?
楽しんでってね
A café?
喫茶店?
It’s a café.
喫茶店だな
Androids going to a café?
アンドロイドが喫茶店に
They might not be here to drink tea.
別にお茶しに来たわけじゃねぇだろう
More importantly, that rule.
それよか　あのルール…
Seems pretty dangerous.
やっぱりヤバイの
Under robot legislation, this is …
ロボット法的には
considered the grey zone.
グレーゾーンだな
It’s too vague.
表現が曖昧すぎる
Listen to me!
って聞けよおい
It’s here.
いた
What?
なんだよ
Isn’t that the android from just now?
さっきのアンドロイド あれだよね
リングがない
There’s no ring.
You can’t be serious.
マジかよ
Is this … in the grey zone?
これってグレーゾーン
Have you ever seen a robot without a ring?
リングのないロボット見たことあるか
This is a serious breach of robot legislation.
超ロボット法違反
You can’t even distinguish them from humans!
人間と区別付かなくなっとる
なんだあいつ
Who the hell is he?
Your order?
ご注文は
This. Eve Blend.
この…イヴブレンド
Evlend.
イヴレンド
That.
それ
I’ll have one too.
同じく
イヴレツー
Two Evlends!
Obey the rule, all right?
ルールは守ってね
Ah. I just thought of something unpleasant.
嫌なこと思いついた
What?
何
This place’s rule.
このカフェのルール
“No discrimination between humans and robots”?
人間とロボット区別しない
That’s why there’s no ring.
だからリングがない
You don’t mean …!
まさか…
Assuming that is true,
でも仮にそうだとしたら
Aki-chan,
アキちゃん起きて
wake up!
he might not be the only problem.
あいつだけの問題じゃねぇかもな
What do you mean?
どういうこと
他の客も全員ルールに従っているとしたらどうだ
What if the other patrons are also obeying the rule …?
Those kids are looking at us.
あの子たち　こっち見てる
ニャー
This is a dangerous café.
ここってヤバイ店
Could be.
かもな
This place …
ここのことさ…
What about it?
なんだよ
Tell your dad?
おじさんに言う?
My old man has nothing to do with this!
親父は関係ねぇよ
What? You guys newbies?
I heard from Nagi-chan!
何が?新入りさんだって?
ナギちゃんから聞いたの
Nagi-chan is the girl at the counter.
ナギちゃんってのはカウンターの彼女ね
Anyway, can I sit here?
それでここ座っていい?
どうやって来たの?誰かの友達?
So, how did you find this place? Are you someone’s friend?
Uh no, we just stumbled across this place.
いや　来たばっかで
Oh I see. Been a long time since we had newcomers!
そうなんだ
でも新しい人久しぶり
Is that s—
It’s always the same people here.
そうなんだ
いつ来ても同じ人ばっか
The one reading a book is Setoro-san, right?
本読んでるのはセトロさんでしょう
On the second floor is Shimei-san and—
二階がシメイさんと…
Ah! Cute little Chie-chan!
可愛いチエちゃん
And over there are Kouji-kun and Rina-chan—aren’t they close?
であっちはコージ君とリナちゃん　仲いいの
And then there’s Nagi-chan, right?
それにナギちゃんでしょう　あとえーと
And who else …
The girl wearing a hat?
帽子かぶってる子
Ah, I’m Akiko. Nice to meet you!
アキコよろしく
I’m Rikuo.
リクオです
Masaki.
真崎
Rikuo-kun and Masaki-kun.
I’ve remembered it!
リクオ君と真崎君　覚えた
Ah! Say, um,
あのさ…えーと
have you seen a female android around?
女性型アンドロイド見なかった
One demerit point.
減点一
ルール違反
You broke the rule.
Oh. Sorry.
You don’t have to say it like that;
そんな言い方しなくてもいいんじゃない
すみません
he’s not used to it yet.
まだ慣れてないんだから
だって
But—
ルール違反はみんなが困るの
Infringing the rule troubles everyone!
Nagi-chan.
ナギちゃん…
はいい子なの
She’s really a good person.
She cares about this place a lot.
この店のことすごく大事にしてるから
Isn’t it just her job?
その割には仕事してねぇじゃん
またすねてる
Oh no, she’s sulking again.
ナギちゃん
Nagi-chan!
ヤバイ店って感じでもないか
I guess it doesn’t feel like a bad place.
つーかむしろ俺はこう言いたい
Rather, I’d like to ask:
Why did she come to a place like this?
なんでこんな店に来てんだ彼女
“Why”?
なんでって
I know.
俺分かった
ロボットと馴れ合いたくて来てんだろう　ドリ系ってやつだな
She wants to befriend robots.
She’s a dori-kei.
You disagree?
肩持つのか
Um. I don’t think it’s like that.
いや　そういうことじゃなくて
Well. You’d get it just by listening to her.
まぁ聞いてみりゃ分かるけどな
We’ll be told off again for breaking the rule.
また言われるよルール違反
There’s more than one way of asking.
そりゃ聞き方一つじゃねぇの
お　来た
Oh. Here she comes.
I brought them back!
取り返したよ
She says she’s sorry.
一応ごめんだって
Uh, I was in the wrong too!
いや　あの　僕も悪かったし
What’cha shy about?
何照れてんだ
That hat suits you.
その帽子似合う
Doesn’t it? I think so too!
でしょう　私もそう思うんだけどね
So … ahem.
それでさ
What is it?
何
Well, it’s something about the world outside this café.
まぁ店の外の話なんだけど
俺んちアンドロイドいねぇんだよ
There are no androids at my place.
Isn’t that uncommon in today’s world?
今時珍しいだろう
You have them too, don’t you? At your place?
いるんだろう　アキコさんちは
いるよ
Yep. We do. That’s why I’m here.
だからここに来てるの
どういうこと
What do you mean?
Here, you can talk to anyone as you please, right?
ここなら誰とでもお話しできるでしょう
いろんなこと分かるじゃない
So you get to know a lot of things.
Like what?
何を
Such as … their feelings, maybe?
相手の…気持ちかな
This has to do with my situation at home.
これは私んちの話ね
私は人間もアンドロイドもみんな家族だって思ってるのよ
I think of both humans and androids as my family.
でもねどんなに私と見た目がそっくりでも
But no matter how similar we appear to each other,
we’re totally different on the inside.
中身は全然違う
似てるけど全然違うのよね
We may look alike, but we’re totally different.
So I often wonder,
だからねよくこう思うの
“What do you think of me?”
あなたは私をどう思ってるのって
それがここにいる理由
That’s why I’m here.
I want to be able to speak with them
and understand more about them.
色々話してもっと分かってあげたいの
だって家族だから
Because we are family after all.
Bah. It’s pouring outside.
ああ　降ってきた
Isn’t your android coming to get you?
リクオとこんの来ないのか
I want to know what they’re thinking about.
「あいつらがなに考えてるか知りたい」って
どう思う
What do you think?
アキコさん関係
Regarding Akiko-san.
Ah, yesterday’s discussion.
ああ　昨日の話
Does someone like her count as a dori-kei?
彼女みたいなのもドリ系っていうのかな
俺は持ってないから分かんねぇけどさ
I don’t have any androids, so I wouldn’t know.
Here’s your umbrella, Mas—
傘をお持ちしました マ…
ああいう使い方するよりはいいんじゃねぇの
She’s way better than someone who uses them like that anyway.
物を大事にする人…なのかな
Could she be … someone who treasures things?
Well, she’s a nice person, right?
まぁいい人じゃね?
That’s true, isn’t it?
そうだよね
What are you relieved about?
なに安心してんだよ
No, it’s not like that.
いや　そんなんじゃないよ
まぁ確かに可愛かった
Well. She certainly was cute.
今日も行ってみっか
Should we go again today?
だから違うって
I said, it’s not like th—
Aki—
アキ…
I’m very sorry for making you wait, Mas—
お待たせして申し訳ありません マ…
かばん　防水　お前だけ帰宅
My bag. Waterproof it. Go on by yourself.
かしこまりました
Acknowledged.
コーヒーです
Here is your coffee.
As I thought. It tastes like that coffee.
やっぱりあの味
入れ方を変えております
I used a different brand.
Huh? I gave no such command!
そんな命令してないぞ
I thought Master would be pleased.
マスターが喜ばれるかと
なに勝手なことしてんだよ
Why did you decide that on your own?
Are you trying to imitate humans too?
お前まで人間の真似するのか
私はアンドロイドです
I am an android.
Not a human, Master.
人間ではありません　マスター
“What do you think of me?”
あなたは私をどう思ってるのって
But no matter how similar we appear to each other,
見た目がそっくりでも
Resembles
we are totally different on the inside.
中身は全然違う
The other way round?
逆か
We may look alike, but we’re totally different.
似てるけど全然違うのよね
Akiko’s Point of View
Resembles
I want to understand more about them.
もっと分かってあげたいの
Because we are family after all.
だって家族だから
Hey. You’re acting like a dori-kei.
ちょっと　ドリ系っぽいんだけど
I have returned.
ただ今戻りました
あれそうじゃない
Isn’t that it?
見覚えがある
Ah. I remember it.
It’s here at last!
やっと来た
お着替えをお持ちしました　マスター
I have brought your change of clothes, Master.
Thank you.
ありがとう
Huh? You thanked it?
お礼とか言ってんの
言わない?
I don’t know. Am I not supposed to?
No way.
言うわけないじゃん
Eh, she’s a dori-kei?
えーあれドリ系
What was that?!
何よそれ
I’m telling you. It said it didn’t go to that café.
だからあの店には行ってないって
Did you do anything aside from your orders?
命令以外のことしたか
I did not.
しておりません
What about that?
あれはどうなんだよ　ほら携帯の
The thing on your mobile phone.
The movement records?
行動記録?
Yeah, that.
それだ
Could it be a problem on this end?
こっちが間違ってるのかな
That’s why I say you trust robots too much.
だからお前ロボット信用しすぎだつーの
Then are you saying Sammy’s lying?
じゃサミィが嘘ついてるわけ
Sa—?
サ…
… Nothing.
いや…うちのアンドロイド
That’s our android.
So it’s called Sammy, huh?
サミィっていうのかあれ
Well. It’s not that I’m really trusting it.
だから別に信用してるわけじゃ
Why don’t you recite the three laws of robotics?
ロボット三原則言ってみろ
We’re not in law school.
別に法学部じゃ
Stop arguing and just remember it already, Master.
いい加減覚えろよマスター
Um. Firstly,
えーと 一条
Do not inflict harm upon humans.
First Law:    A robot may not injure a human being or, through inaction,
allow a human being to come to harm.
Three Laws of Robotics
人間に危害を加えない
That’s right.
おし
Secondly,
二条
Obey commands from humans, unless this contravenes the first rule.
Second Law:    A robot must obey orders given to it by human beings,
except where such orders would conflict with the First Law.
Three Laws of Robotics
一条に反しない限り
人間の命令に従う
Oh. You do remember after all.
覚えてんじゃん
Thirdly—
三条…
Was there a third?
ってあったっけ
Protect yourself.
Third Law:    A robot must protect its own existence, as long as such protection does not conflict with the First or Second Law.
Three Laws of Robotics
自分の身を守る
These are the codes of conduct for a robot.
これがロボットの行動原理だ
In other words, that’s all there is to it.
つまりそういうこった
どういうこった
What do you mean?
That is to say,
だから嘘をつくなって原則はねぇんだよ
there’s no law against lying.
First Law:    Do not inflict harm upon humans
Second Law:    Obey human commands
Third Law:    Protect self
No way!
嘘
It’s surprising how you don’t know this.
案外知らねぇんだよなこれ
So, no matter what Sammy-chan says,
まぁサミィちゃんの言うことは信用できないってこった
you can’t trust it fully.
It goes shopping this afternoon, right?
午後はお買い物だったな
What?
な…なにが
I’m talking about Sammy-chan!
サミィちゃんだよ
Just shopping, it said.
買い物するだけだって
There’s no choice but to confirm for ourselves if that is the truth.
それが本当かどうかは
直接確かめるしかねぇな
We’re going in after all?
やっぱり行く
んだよ確かめたくねぇのか
What is it now? Don’t you want to confirm it?
That’s not it.
そういうわけじゃ…
Then that’s fine.
じゃいいだろう
Hm! All right.
いいよ
What’s with that?
なんだよそれ
I said I’m going!
だから行くって
Then let’s go.
じゃ行こうぜ
Ah. Let’s go.
ああ　行こう
Ah. Welcome.
いらっしゃい
Hm?
どうしたの
What’s up?
It’s too early to be relieved.
安心すんのは早いな
It might come in later.
これから来んのかもしんねぇぞ
ここで待つの
We’re going to wait here?
For now, shall we stick around until dinner?
とりあえず　晩飯まで粘るか
But I don’t really want to confront it here.
ばったり出くわしたくないんだけど
Isn’t it all right here?
ここでいいんじゃね?
But I’m short-sighted.
僕ド近眼なんだよね
You can’t see it, even from here?
こっからでも見えねぇのかよ
After all, I can’t see anything if I take my glasses—
だって裸眼で0.1以下だし
ニャー
ニャー　ニャー
Chie-chan! Come down from there!
チエちゃん 下りておいで
I’m a cat!
猫なの
Oh. I’m so sorry, lads.
いや申し訳ない　お兄さん方
It’s best for kids to play around freely.
子供は自由に遊ぶのが一番　ですよね
Isn’t it?
Ah, freely.
ああ
自由だな
Come along. Give it up now.
ほら 止しなさいって
Those round things are weird.
あれが変なの
Chie. There’s something you want to eat, isn’t there?
チエちゃん食べたいものがあるんだよね
I am a cat!
猫なの
And ice-cream!
あんねアイス
If you don’t sit down, you won’t get to eat it.
椅子に座らないと食べられないよ
アイス　アイス
Heh. Sorry about that.
失礼
Once something catches her attention, she forgets all else.
興味を持ったらほかの事はお構いなしでして
It’s a piano.
ピアノだ
Are you going to play it?
弾くのか
I told you. I’ve quit playing.
だからもうやめたって
I’ll play it.
弾くのはね
That old man and the kid are both human, right?
あのおじさんと子供人間だよね
No matter how you look at them, they’re human. But you know—
どう見ても人間だな
つっても
What?
なに
Akiko appears to be human here as well.
アキコもここじゃ人間に見えたけどな
Huh?
How lonely.
私寂しい
I will be lonely too.
僕だって寂しいよ
Can’t we meet every day?
毎日はダメ?
No. I have my job.
うん　仕事もあるし
You are meeting other women outside, aren’t you?
外で女の人と会ってるんでしょう
No. That’s not it.
いや そんなことないよ
私を一人にしないでくださいね
Please don’t leave me by myself.
Yes. I know.
分かってる
Shall we go somewhere else?
場所　変えようか
What were you doing?
何してるのさっきから
Socializing.
交流を深めてます
Order something already.
注文してよ
Two blends.
ブレンド二つ
Evlends for two!
イヴレンド二つ
It’s ice cream!
アイスだ
Here. Sorry, Chie-chan.
はい　お待たせチエちゃん
A cat’s tongue can take the cold.
猫舌は　冷たいの平気なの
You’re scared, aren’t you?
お前さ　怖いんだろう
Scared of what?
何が
Scared that Sammy-chan will come.
サミィちゃんが来るのが
なに言ってんだよ
What are you on about?
That your robot is someplace unknown,
doing whatever it wants.
自分のロボットが知らないところで勝手なことをしてたらな
“Violating human authority!”
「人間の尊厳が侵されている」ってか
Is that it?
Your dad said that?
それおじさん
Well. I don’t know.
まぁ俺にゃ分かんねぇけどな
Don’t even have one.
持ってねぇし
Why don’t you?
なんで持ってないのさ
Ah. You’re here.
来た
I’m here!
来たよ
サミィが嘘つく理由が分かんない
I don’t get why Sammy would lie.
I find it harder to make sense of ring-less robots.
俺はリングなしのロボットの方が分かんねぇよ
I’ll be right back.
ちょっと行ってくる
リクオ君
Rikuo-kun!
What? What’s up?
なに　どうしたの
Eh? What?
いやーもう
You’re completely different.
全然違う
Heh? Really? I’m so happy!
そう　嬉しい
Uh, by the wa—
あ…あのさ
じゃなくて…質問
That’s not it. Question.
Where’s the ring on top of your head?
その…リングは　頭の上の
It’s off. If I don’t look human, it’ll be a rule violation.
消してるよ
人間と同じに見えないとルール違反だもん
But the robot laws—
でもロボット法
All right. This conversation ends here.
はい　この話終わり
Ah, Chie-chan!
チエちゃん
猫なの
I’m a cat.
Chie-chan. What’s up?
どうしたのチエちゃん
He’s wearing something weird.
変なの付けてる
Something weird?
変なのって
ニャー　ニャー
What do you want of me, Blade Runner?
私に何か　ブレードランナー
Shouldn’t you do a better job of observing me?
もっとうまく監視したらどうだ
Having a man’s intense gaze on me …
男の纏わり付くような視線は
is far from comfortable.
...気持ちのいいものじゃない
I’m sorry.
すみません
Violate the rules, and you won’t have fun here.
ルールに反抗的ではここは楽しまない
今日が賑やかですね
No; rather, it would be meaningless to be here.
いや ここにいる意味がないらしい
That’s what I’ve been told.
まぁ 受け売りだがね
持ってないもん
I don’t have it!
今日はいいの
Ah. Is today all right?
Well. Please give my regards to your friend.
それでは 君のご友人によろしく
あとで返してもらえると思うよ　多分
You’ll get them back eventually, probably.
Probably?
多分
She hid my hat before as well.
前に帽子隠されたことあったので
My glasses got taken.
メガネ取られた
So where was your hat?
ね　帽子は
帽子って
My hat?
She hid it right?
隠されたって
Ah, that’s right. And then I asked where it was, and Chie-chan had it all along!
ああ　そうそう
それでどこに隠したか問い詰めたらね　ずっとチーちゃんが持ってたの
Please come again!
また来てね
持ってたって
She had it?
She hid it inside her panties!
パンツの中に挟んでた
She must have taken a liking to it.
すっごく気に入ってたのにね
Sorry. Something came up.
悪い　俺用事できた
What a nice atmosphere, huh.
いい雰囲気じゃん
What’s up with Masaki-kun?
真崎君どうしたの
Dunno.
さぁ
It won’t open now.
今は開かないわよ
What?
When someone leaves,
it stays locked for some time.
誰か帰ったらしばらくロックされるの
Why?
なんでだよ
Privacy is precious.
プライバシーって大切よ
えーと
Um. Is this size all right?
このサイズでいいの
Yup.
うん
We have larger sizes.
もっと大きいのもあるけど
If it’s too big, the other household members will find out.
あんまり大きいと家の人に見つかるから
All right then. Hold on a second.
はいはい　ちょっと待ってて
I’ll get you a good blend.
いい豆入れてあげるから
What should we do, Rina-chan?
どうしようか リナちゃん
I’m really sorry.
Please leave first.
申し訳ございません　先にお通りください
はい　今日の分
Here. Today’s coffee.
Sorry for always taking things from your café.
いつもごめんねお店のもの
Did they like it?
気に入ってくれた
I wonder if they did.
気に入って…くれてるのかな
You could always ask them yourself.
自分から聞くって手もあるわよ
I can’t do that!
それはダメ
Why?
どうして
He hates it when I try to start things.
私から何かをするのが嫌いなの
“Don’t do things on your own,” he’d say.
勝手なことするなって
It’s all right.
大丈夫
He will definitely understand you.
きっと分かってくれる
Well, isn’t this café’s rule a local one?
だって　たかがローカルルールだろう
You can’t compare it with the robot laws.
ロボット法とは比較にならないんじゃ
またルール違反
You’re violating the rule again. You’ll get caught.
言いつけるよ
You won’t say no matter what?
どうしてもダメ
ナギちゃんには内緒にしてあげるから
I’ll keep it a secret from Nagi-chan, so this conversation ends here.
この話は終わり
Secret?
内緒
So you really can keep secrets.
やっぱり内緒にできるんだ
Quite a strange conversation you’re having.
随分と変な話をしてますね
Everyone has a thing or two that they’re hiding.
誰にだって隠し事の一つや二つ
Well, but she’s an—
いや だって彼女は…
In this café,
there is to be no discrimination
between humans and robots.
Ah, umm …
えーと
I’m also keeping something from this girl.
私もこの子に秘密にしていることがあります
I’m not saying that I won’t lie to her either.
嘘だってつかないわけじゃない
But it’s for this child’s sake.
でもそれはこの子のためです
Akiko-san is keeping that secret of yours …
アキコさんが内緒にするのも
for your sake too, isn’t it?
リクオ君のためでしょう
“Do not inflict harm upon humans.”
人間に危害を加えない
“These are the codes of conduct for a robot.”
これがロボットの行動原理だ
“Did you do anything besides your orders—”
命令以外のことしたか
“I did not.”
しておりません
Because I will get hurt.
僕が傷つくから
… For my sake?
僕のため
To begin with,
もっとも
she didn’t tell you where your glasses were because …
メガネの在り処を言わなかったのは
haha, she just wanted to play with you, isn’t it?
遊んでほしかったからでしょうが
They’re not in her panties?
パンツの中じゃ
She seems to have handed it to someone.
誰かに渡したそうです
Oh. It’s already this late.
もうこんな時間
Are you heading back?
帰るの
I have to prepare dinner.
夕食の支度しないと
Thanks for this.
これありがとう
Hey.
あの…
Ah. You finally realized.
やっと気が付いた
Why did you keep quiet about it?
なんで黙ってたんですか
You didn’t ask.
聞かれなかったから
So the customers and staff here are chummy huh?
客も店員も仲良しってわけですか
What?
あれ
Damn it!
くそ
Rikuo-kun.
リクオ君
What’s this? Dammit!
なんだよ畜生
Rikuo-kun.
リクオ君
… Doing things on her own!
勝手なことしやがって
She’s my—!
あいつは俺の…
Sit down!
座りなさい
… Yes.
はい
This cup’s on the house.
一杯くらいサービスしてあげる
That girl …
あの子
when did she first arrive?
初めて来たのはいつだったかな
She was a bit confused at first,
最初は戸惑ってたんだけど
だんだん打ち解けてきて
but she gradually warmed to us.
Warmed to you?
打ち解ける？
うん
Yup. She was able to talk to us about many things.
色々話してくれるようになったの
The mother who buys her clothes.
服を買ってくれるお母さん
Her occasional nightmares.
たまに見る怖い夢
The boy who would not play the piano any more.
ピアノを弾かなくなった男の子
Just the other day, she came in.
それでこの間言ってきたの
コーヒーをうまく入れたいって
Said she wanted to make good coffee.
She seems troubled by many things.
色々と悩んでるみたい
Troubled?
悩む
You don’t understand, do you?
分からないのね
Whether the things one does are right,
自分のしていることが正しいのか
or wrong.
間違っているのか
Here.
はい
As long as you are following the rule,
ルールさえ守ってくれたら
Time of Eve is always open to welcome you.
イヴの時間はいつでもご来店をお待ちしております
So, in the end, I lost sight of him there.
で結局そこで見失っちまった
You followed him outside?
外まで追いかけたの
あのロッポの頭の上を確かめたかったんだよ
I wanted to check if he had anything above his head.
That café is definitely up to something—
あの店　ぜってぇなんかあるぞ
Um.
あのさ
また　行ってみようと思うんだけど
I was thinking of going there again sometime.
Oh. I’ll come with you!
付き合うぜ
This time we’ll definitely unravel this mystery!
こうなったら徹底的に謎を暴いてやる
All right. See you then.
Say “hi” to Robot Sammy-chan for me.
よし　じゃな
ロボットサミィちゃんによろしくな
Question.
質問
なんでしょうか
What is it?
Um, that café …
えーと
あの店
Master, I am sorr—
マスター　申し訳あり…
Coffee.
コーヒー
かしこまりました
Acknowledged.
最近のコーヒー
Recently, the coffee’s …
been quite delicious, I think.
おいしい…かも
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
I saw a lot of interesting things.
色々と面白いものが見られましてね
まだ特定には至りませんが
But I haven’t pinned down anything specific.
Anything to do with the Ethics Committee?
倫理委員会とは無関係ね
If there were, they wouldn’t have used such a careless shadow.
だったらあんな下手な尾行はしないでしょう
I’ll let it swim free for a while, see where that takes us.
しばらく泳がせて様子を見ます
Indeed.
そうね
Chairwoman Ashimori.
芦森主任　現状において個性が定着しつつあります
As it is, it seems individuality is beginning to manifest.
This means the suppression circuit is—
これはもう抑制回路…
“Assumptions distract from the truth.”
先入観は真実を遠ざける
That’s what Shiotsuki would say.
潮月ならそう言うはずよ
I will continue my duties.
続行します
Love isn’t present there.
Ethics Committee
Hasn’t this commercial been appearing really often lately?
最近多くないこのCM
Status: Rikuo.
ステータス：リクオ
12:03 p.m.: Left the house.
午後12時3分より外出しております
Having lunch outside.
昼食は外で取るそうです
I’m just saying,
私が言うのもなんだけど
but you come here really often in the afternoons, don’t you?
昼間からよく来るわね
Hmm … Skipping classes?
サボリ?
Compensatory holiday.
振り替え休日
That’s not something a café assistant should say.
店員が言う言葉じゃねぇな
Sorry. Rikuo-kun aside, I thought
Masaki-kun was a bit of a delinquent.
ごめん
リクオ君はともかく
真崎君はちょっと悪い子だと思ってた
He’s on a scholarship. Quite unexpected.
特待生なんだよ　意外だろうけど
Don’t say anything unnecessary!
余計なこと言うなつーの
It’s not something to hide anyway.
隠すことないのに
Hey. If you’re looking for someone to talk to, there are other people.
おしゃべりする相手ならほかにもいるわよ
Do you always carry that with you?
ああ二階はちょっと待って
Yeah. I take various pictures with it.
色々撮っておきたいんだ
Well. We’ll get around to it eventually.
まぁそのうちな
Thanks for the meal.
ご馳走様
You’re welcome. I’ll bring your after-meal Evlend over.
どういたしまして
食後のイヴレンド持ってくるわね
Evlend. Evlend.
イヴレンド　イヴレンド
What?
なんだよ
I’ve stopped feeling uncomfortable about it!
違和感なくなってきた
Ah! Not my reading glasses!
老眼鏡はダメ
チエちゃん返してよ
Chie! Give it back!
I’m a cat!
猫なの
座ってるだけじゃ意味ないかもね
There’s no point just sitting around.
Well. I just want to know what this café is all about.
俺はこの店がなんなのか知りたいだけだ
I’ve no intention of getting close to any of the robots.
ロボットと馴れ合うつもりはねぇよ
We don’t know about anyone other than Akiko-san.
アキコさん以外はまだ分かんないよ
What about them, to my right?
あれはどうだ　もっと右
A dori-kei getting intimate with his own android.
ドリ系が自分のアンドロイドを連れてきてる
No further explanation needed.
これ以上説明要らねぇよな
どこ見てんだよ
Where are you staring?
Come on.
お前さ
I wasn’t staring!
見てないよ
No, you were—
見てたじゃん
I’m saying I wasn’t!
見てないって
You stared.
いや見てた
I wasn’t staring!
見てない
You were staring.
見てた
I wasn’t staring!
見てない
You were staring!
You two sure get along well.
見てた
仲いいわね
I’ve never been told that before!
No way!
言われたことねぇ
そんなことないって
Just two boys getting all excited is pretty lonely you know.
男二人で盛り上がっても寂しいわよ
The next time I catch you staring—
今度変な目で見たら
見てないって
I wasn’t staring!
何をだよ
At what?
コージ君が羨ましいんだ
So you’re jealous of Kouji-kun.
だから違うって
I’m not!
He’s just very interesting, right?
まぁ興味深いよな　だろう
Hey!
ね
こっち来ない
Why don’t you join us here?
暗い
怖い
Wouldn’t it be better not to do anything unnecessary?
余計なことはしない方がいいんじゃないか
Was it unnecessary, really?
余計かしら
I think it would have made more sense to let things develop on their own.
自生に任せるのが筋と思うが
Four people will stimulate more conversation, right?
四人のほうが話しも弾むんじゃない
He’s Kouji. I’m Rina.
彼はコージ　私はリナと申します
Ah, nice to meet you.
あ　どうも
I’m Masaki. This guy here is Rikuo.
俺真崎　こいつリクオ
Next time you stare, I’ll smack you.
次見たら手出すからな
I wasn’t staring!
見てないって
見てた
Was I?
Subconsciously huh?
無意識か
You two …
You two sure get along well.
仲いい…
仲いいんですね
No way!
Never heard that before!
そんなことないって
言われたことね…
こともないか
Or have I?
ニャー
Ah. You sure come here often.
よく来てますよねここ
Yes.
はい
Do you two come here together?
二人で一緒に来てんのか
No. Separately.
いえ別々です
弾んでいるな見事に
It sure is going splendidly, huh?
Ah, is that the Cinema Tide?
それってシネマタイド
May I have a look?　見せてもらっていい
Can I have a look?
Does he like it?
お好きなんですか
スイッチそこ
The switch is there.
What?
Ah, it’s beautiful.
きれいだね
Can you see a preview of it?
プリビューって見れるの
Yes, if you press that triangle over there.
うん　そこの三角押して
He’s just making conversation, isn’t he?
話題作りだろう
It’s got 500.
500積んでるから
Oh. That’s right.
そうだ
あの…
It has M-link, so maybe …
エムリンクだから多分
Um, hold on …
あの…ちょっと
Cine-Tide sure is awesome after all!
やっぱりシネタいいな
Um. That’s about it, so …
えーとじゃそんな感じで
How do I turn this off?
外すときどうするんだ
What is this?
何これ
これは違うんだよ
It’s not what you think.
Your heart … it’s so distant.
遠いんです　あなたの心が
何度会っても　寄り添っていても
No matter how many times we meet,
or how intimate we get,
I feel uneasy.
不安で
I finally understand why.
やっと理由が分かりました
Please don’t leave me alone.
私を一人にしないでくださいね
That’s quite the drama.
ドラマだな
My fault … I guess?
僕のせい…かな
It is your fault.
お前のせいだ
Sorry about the wait!
はいお待たせ
Wh-what?
な…なに
What is it?
何よ
I’ll go take care of things.
なんとかしてきます
What’s wrong?
どうしたの
Well. What do you call this? A scene of carnage?
まぁなんだ
修羅場?
Protected witness has arrived.
R隊到着
I was deployed as my Master’s guard.
私はマスターの護衛を実行しました
Then, Kouji is …?
じゃ　コージさんって
What have I been doing until now?!
僕は今までなんてことを
It seems the emergency repairs were incomplete.
応急処置が不完全だったようです
You came here for Kouji’s, uh—
ここに来るのはコージ…その
君のマスターの護衛ってこと
your Master’s protection?
No. I took my own initiative.
いえ
私自身の意思です
That leg; shouldn’t it be looked at by the maker?
それメーカー修理に出した方が
I cannot have anything to do with my legal maker.
私は正規のメーカーと関係を持つことができません
If my maker were to find out about me,
私のことがメーカーに知られれば
my Master will be put in a disadvantageous position.
マスターが不利益を被るでしょう
That aside, I would like to be here a little longer too.
それよりも私は少しでも長くここにいたい
Not even going for repairs.
修理もしないなんて
In this café, I’m the one who acts least like a human.
この店でもっとも人間らしく振舞えていないのは
Am I right?
私です　そうでしょう
I wouldn’t be surprised if I were destroyed sooner rather than later.
私はいつ破壊されてもおかしくありません
だから　使うことのない学習機能に自立的抵抗をかけているのだと思います
That is why I am autonomously resisting my useless learning functions.
Kouji treated someone like me …
コージは
こんな私を人間の女性として扱ってくれます
like a human female.
だから私はここで…幸せなんだと思います
I think that’s why I am happy here.
But, the woman in that photograph …
でも…
写真の女の人
You’re kind, aren’t you?
優しいんですね
But it’ll be all right,
でも大丈夫です
because I think Kouji’s kindness will not change.
コージの優しさは変わらないと思うから
やっぱり
I guess …
I’m going back.
戻ります
Excuse me!
あのさ
コーヒーが
The coffee—
When my coffee’s flavor changed,
コーヒーの味が変わってて
I was angry at first.
最初は怒ったんだけど
Then, after I understood various things, I was a little glad,
色々分かったら　少しだけ嬉しくなって
though she isn’t human …
えーと
相手は人間じゃないのに
Tell him!
言いなよ
Tell him what you want to say, even if he’s a human!
言いたいことは　相手が人間でも
なぜそう思うのですか
Why … do you think that?
You knew, didn’t you, your feelings at that moment?
知っているんですね　その時の気持ち
Probably.
多分ね
How did I end up saying such things?
こういうこと言うようになっちゃって
はい?
こっちが本命ってわけか
So you’re serious about this one?
さっきから気になってんだよ
Something’s been bothering me since just now.
There is not a single picture of you with Rina.
お前とリナが一緒に映ってる写真が一枚もない
But I guess you couldn’t have such a thing.
撮るわけにはいかないよな
It would be bad if people knew you had an imaginary lover.
恋人ごっこが外にバレたらまずいだろう
No; if this one is a robot too—
いや　案外こっちもロボットか
She’s not a robot!
ロボットじゃない
All the more reason then.
じゃなお更だ
What are you doing here?
ここで何してんだよ
She’s not my imaginary lover!
恋人ごっこなんかじゃない
Then are you saying this relationship is for real?
じゃ本気だってのかよ
“There is love.”
愛情があるとか　吐かすんじゃねぇだろうな
That’s not what you’re trying to say, is it?
What you’re trying to say is,
君はこう言いたいんだ
“For humans, a human partner is best.”
人間には人間のパートナーが一番だって
So you do understand that.
分かってんじゃんか
I understand.
分かってる
分かっている
I know that.
As you said, Rina and I cannot transcend a human–android relationship.
君の言うとおり　僕とリナは人間とアンドロイドの関係に過ぎない
分かり合えないことはあると思う
I think there are things we cannot understand about each other.
There’s no way you could understand each other.
分かり合えるわけねぇだろう
僕はね
You see.
I want to help my Master.
マスターを助けたいんだ
My Master is very much like Rina.
僕のマスター　リナとよく似ている
I want to help my Master.
僕はマスターを助けたい
Yesterday too; I saw a lot of people.
昨日もいろんな人を見ました
I don’t care about that.
そんなの知らない
But, Master.
しかしマスター
Master, you should look for a new partner.
マスターは新たなパートナーを見つけるべきです
A human—
人間の…
That’s enough. I’m tired.
もういいの
疲れた
You’re enough, Kouji.
コージがいい
I’m going to become a robot.
あたしがロボットになるの
So stay with me always.
ずっと傍にいて
My Master is morbidly dependent on me.
マスターは僕に依存しきっている
But I don’t know what to do about that.
でもどうすればいいのか分からなかった
When I first met Rina, I thought she was just like my Master.
リナと会ったとき
この人はマスターと一緒なんだと思った
僕に触れる仕草も　たまに見せる表情も
The way she behaves and touches me,
and the fleeting expressions she sometimes shows me.
I want to know more about Rina, to better understand my Master.
僕はリナのことをもっと知ってマスターを理解したい
I want to help my Master.
マスターを助けたいんだ
The First Law!
第一条だ
About all this; can you keep it from Rina?
このことを　リナには黙っていてもらえませんか
店のルールか
The café’s rule?
傷つけられないんです誰も
I don’t want to hurt anyone.
Convenient for you huh?
勝手だな
Aren’t you a failure?
ダメ人間じゃねぇか
みんなが幸せにはなれないんでしょうね
It seems no one can really attain happiness.
ありがとう
Thank you.
We should
get out of here.
In that case, please excuse us.
それでは　失礼します
I guess there are all sorts.
いろんなのがいるよね
Of humans?
人間が
Androids too.
アンドロイドも
Sorry about hitting you earlier.
叩いて悪かったな
Your eyes were right.
お前の目が正しかったわけだ
I should have taken a good look myself.
俺もじっくり見ときゃよかった
Masaki.
マサキ
Have you awoken?
目覚めたの
I’m not a pubescent junior high student!
俺は思春期の中学生か
でも リナの方は
But, Rina is—
No! It’s the other way round, isn’t it?
いや逆だろう
Hold on.
待てよ
What did Rina say, again?
リナはなんて言ったんだ
You came here for Kouji’s, uh—
ここに来るのはコージ…その　君のマスターの護衛ってこと
your Master’s protection?
いえ
No.
She never once said her Master was Kouji.
自分のマスターがコージとは一言も言ってねぇよな
Master
言ってない
She didn’t say it.
Master
店の外で　二人は無関係
They have nothing to do with each other outside of this café?
Master
But they both said the other is human.
でもどっちも相手が人間だって言ってる
Human
Something’s off—
食い違ってる…
Here you go! Thanks for waiting.
はいお待たせ
They might not have realized about each other.
気づいてないかもねお互いに
Yup. That’s it for hints.
はい　ヒントはここまで
Human
It’s the same!
同じだよ
Will you please explain this properly?
ちゃんと説明しろよ
Partners not knowing what the other is;
相手がどちらか分からないのは
it’s the same with androids.
アンドロイドも同じってこと
They are interested in each other.
あの二人はお互いに興味を持ってて
For different reasons, that is.
違う理由でな
お互いに隠してることもある
They also have things they hide from each other.
So what?
それはなんだよ
It’s like normal love.
普通の恋愛っぽい
That should be a good thing, right?
いいこと言うじゃない
But don’t interfere too much.
でも　あんまり邪魔しちゃダメよ
Love between androids …
アンドロイド同士の恋愛
疑似恋愛だろう
Pseudo-love huh?
それで先日の写真の女性
So that woman in the photo the other day.
Who was that?
どなたなんですか
えーと
アンドロイドが三角関係
A love triangle between androids.
It’s a bit hard to explain.
説明が難しいな
A difficult-to-explain woman, huh?
説明が難しい女性
Androids tangled in blind love.
アンドロイドの痴情のもつれ
Don’t think deviant thoughts!
変な突っ込み入れないでよ
You’ll tell me about it properly someday, right?
いつかはっきりさせますからね
いや…そうなの
I will?
お帰りなさいませ　マスター
Welcome home, Master.
Nao-chan and Mom have gone out for dinner.
Sammy-chan, please take care of the rest!!
What did you put on your head?
何頭につけてんだよ
Do you not like it?
お気に召しませんか
Vagrant Robot Reporting Hotline
Vagrant androids are dangerously likely to have corrupted thought logic. Report all discoveries immediately.
This is a request from the Ethics Committee.
倫理委員会からのお願いです
Currently, the Ethics Committee …
現在　倫理委員会では
is undertaking independent recovery of vagrant robots …
マスターの管理下から外れて放置されている
that have been removed from the supervision of their Masters …
浮浪ロボットの自主回収を進めております
これは何を描いたものですか
What is this drawing of?
自分のこと分からないの
You can’t recognise yourself?!
私…ですか
This is me?
That’s right! It is a drawing of ✲✲✲✲!
そうだよ
…の絵だよ
Isn’t it quiet?
静かね
You mean there are no customers.
つーか客いねぇし
Oh, but …
Huh?
あれ
Have they gone back?
帰ったのかな
This really is a strange café, isn’t it?
本当に変な店だよな いろんな意味で
In various ways.
あ…あのさえーと　ナギさんってなんでここで働いてるの
Ex-excuse me!
Nagi-san, why do you work here?
You can just call me Nagi.
ナギでいいわよ
Because I like it here.
ここが好きだから
I also like the people who come here.
ここに来る人もね
So on days like today, when I can’t see my favorite customers’ faces, I get lonely.
だから今日みたいに大好きなお客さんの顔が見えないのは寂しいわ
Um, what about us …?
あの…僕らは
Huh? What?
えっ　なに
This. Can I get a refill?
これ　お代わり
I’ll just bring out the beans. Please wait a while.
豆出してくるね
ちょっと待ってて
Enjoy your stay.
ゆっくりしてってね
It really is quiet, isn’t it?
本当静かだな
It’s an luh model.
LUH型だ
A houseroid model released when we were in primary school!
小学生くらいの時に出たハウスロイド
It’s still around, huh?
まだいたんだ
I’ve never seen one before.
見たことねぇな
They weren’t very popular back then.
あまり流行らなかったんだよ
使いにくいって苦情が多くて
There were many complaints that they were hard to use.
It’s shaking pretty badly though.
すっげぇ揺れてんだけど
Do you have some business here?
We’re just customers.
店に用事?
僕ら客なんだけど
Do you understand what a “customer” is?
客　分かる?
I am also a “customer.”
私も客です
おい
I am Masaki. This guy is Rikuo.
俺は真崎　こいつはリクオ
であんたは
So. Who are you?
Wh-what are you doing?
なに言ってんの
Normally, humans would introduce themselves.
普通人間は自己紹介するもんだぜ
Introduction is a process wherein I communicate my name, is it not?
自己紹介とは　私の名前をお伝えするということですか
This guy is trying to imitate humans.
人間のふりしてるつもりだぜこいつ
Heh. It’s abiding by the rule.
ルール守ってんだ
That’s right! It is a drawing of ✲✲✲✲!
そうだよ　…だよ
I am called … ✲✲✲✲.
私は　「…」と申します
Why did you cover your ears?
なぜ耳を塞ぐのですか
If I do not communicate my name,
the introduction cannot be completed.
名前をお伝えしなければ　自己紹介は完了しません
In other words, I will be unable to verify my status as a human.
つまり私が人間であることを照明できません
My name is ✲✲✲✲.
私の名前は「…」
It-it’s all right! You don’t have to overdo it.
いいんだよ　無理にしなくても
Overdo what?
何をですか
The introduction!
だから自己紹介
Why is that? Just a moment ago,
なぜですか　真崎様は先ほど
“Normally, humans would introduce themselves.”
「普通人間は自己紹介するもんだぜ」
とおっしゃいましたが
… is what you said.
Masaki! This one cannot deal with fuzzy interactions!
マサキ
こいつに曖昧な会話はダメだ
What should we do?!
どうすんだよ
Anyway, if we don’t let it introduce itself—
とにかく自己紹介させないと
What about that sound?!
あの音を
For the time being, we’ll have to bear with it.
とりあえず聞かなきゃ
We’re sorry! Go ahead and say it!
悪かった
じゃ言ってみろ
Like I said, I am ✲✲✲✲.
ですから　「…」です
It-it’s a nice name huh.
い…いいお名前ですね
I think so too.
私もそう思います
It’s very important to me.
大切な名前です
That’s wonderful.
そりゃ結構
Where do I find a restroom?
お手洗いはどちらでしょうか
That broken machine,
でもあの壊れ方　あんなになるまでほっとかなくても
it was left alone, to fall into such disrepair.
It should be returned to the maker for repairs—
メーカーに修理に出すとか
You’re talking like that again.
またそういう話してる
But I think today—
でも今日のはさすがに…
Rikuo-kun.
リクオ君
He is a customer.
彼はお客
You already understand that, don’t you?
もう分かってるでしょう
Everyone who comes here is the same.
ここに来る人はみんな同じ
Excuse me.
失礼します
Welcome. What would you like to order?
いらっしゃいませ
ご注文は
Something feels wrong.
なんか変じゃね?
It might not be able to decide.
判断できないのかも
This is something new for it after all.
初めてのことだろうし
Ouch!
あっち
注文　これもう一杯
Order! One more cup of this!
I would like to order what Rikuo-sama is having.
リクオ様と同様の注文をします
Yep. Two Evlends!
はい　イヴレツー
Going to drink the coffee?
飲めんのかコーヒー
Three cups might be pushing it.
三杯目はきついかも
No. I meant the robot.
いやロボットが
あの口はただのスピーカーだよ
That mouth is just a speaker.
What if it tries to drink, imitating humans?
人間の真似して飲んだら
If it does that …
そしたら
Hey. Hold on! The Third Law prohibits robot suicide!
待てよおい
Three Laws of Robotics
Third Law
A robot must protect its own existence, as long as such protection
does not conflict with the First or Second Law.
第三条　ロボットは自殺できない
Does this guy not understand that drinking could be dangerous?
飲んだらヤバイことくらい分かってんだろうこいつ
That is true. It wouldn’t try to drink … right?
そうだよね
飲むわけない…よね
Is something the matter?
どうかしましたか
Coffee is … dangerous!
コーヒーが
ヤバイ
な…なにやってるの
Wh-what are you doing?
なにって
What?
Thanks for waiting on the Evlend!
イヴレンド お待たせしました
な…なんで
Why?!
It’s for the customer to drink, isn’t it?
お客様がお飲みになるためでしょう
Don’t say such weird things.
変なこと言わないの
Hey, hold it! wait!
おい　ちょっと待って
Cut the switch!
スイッチ切れ
I haven’t done this before!
やったことないよ
Or-order it! Just order it!
命令だ
命令すりゃいいだろう
Oh. I see!
そうか
Drop the cup! It’s an order!
カップを下ろせ　命令だ
Why?
なぜですか
“Why”?
なぜって
She said,
あの方は
“It’s for the customer to drink, isn’t it?
「お客様がお飲みになるためでしょう」
“Don’t say such weird things.”
「変なこと言わないの」
とおっしゃいました
… a while ago.
私はお客です
I am a customer.
Ah! Question!
あっ　質問
What is it?
なんでしょうか
Um.
えーと
H-h-how old are you?
お…おいくつですか
Age-wise? This year I will be eight years old.
年齢のことですね
今年で八歳になります
He probably means that he was manufactured eight years ago.
多分八年前に作られたってこと
You thought I was a bit big to be an eight-year-old human, didn’t you?
八歳の人間にしては大きいと思いましたね
Not really—
いやんなこと…
No, Masaki-sama. It was written all over your face.
いえ　真崎様　そういう顔をしています
Why’re you only concerned with this sort of detail?
なんでここだけ細かいんだよ
しかしながら私は八歳
But I am eight years …
Eight years …
八歳
Eight …
八…
おい
論理とルールが矛盾してる
Its logic is in conflict with the rule. It cannot answer!
八…
答えられないんだ
What should we do?!
どうすんだよ
Well! There are many types of eight-year-olds!
いや八歳って言っても色々ですから
There are other eight-year-old humans who look like me, is that right?
八歳で私と同体型の人間が存在するということですか
That’s right!
そうそう
I do not have data about that.
私のデータにはありません
Please explain in detail.
詳しく教えてください
Th-th-th-there’s a frequent visitor to this café!
こ…この店によく来る人なんですよ
Someone who comes to this café, and is eight years old?
この店に来る方で八歳なんですね
What is this person’s name?
お名前は
Sh-she’s called Chie-chan! Well, she’s …
チエちゃんって言って
そりゃもう八歳…未満です
8 Years
Eight years old … not quite.
Not quite eight years
そうそう　でかいよな
That’s right! She’s big! Well, her voice is.
声とか…
The most important thing is that you believe me.
信じていただけて何よりです
What is your job?
仕事は何を
I helped with child care.
育児のお手伝いをしておりました
Ehh, child care huh?
育児ですか
Yes. For a couple and their only son.
はい
ご両親とご子息が…
Hey! Help me out here!
ちょっと　相手してよ
What?
なに
It’s tough doing this by myself, you know.
一人じゃきついんだけど
I am a customer.
私はお客です
Thanks for the coffee.
ご馳走様でした
A liquid-storage tank …!
給水タンク
What was all that hard work for?
今までの苦労はなんだったんだ
The danger has passed, I guess?
危機が去ったかな
Excuse me. Where might Nagi-san be?
失礼　ナギさんはどちらに
この子の昼寝の番をしてたら　私まで眠りこけてしまいました
While looking after her during her nap,
I fell asleep myself.
Something weird is sitting there!
変なの座ってる
It’s not nice to say such things.
そんなこと言っちゃダメだよ
Chie-chan, let’s go back?
チエちゃん　帰ろうね
I’m a cat!
猫なの
Umm.
あの…
Excuse me.
失礼
She’s called Chie-chan.
「チエちゃんって言って」
Is Chie-chan the one who is not quite eight years old?
チエちゃんとは八歳未満の方ですか
What?
He, he is Chie-chan!
この人チエちゃん
あなた何を言ってるんですか
What are you saying?
ニャー
This person is …
こちら様は
I’m a cat!
猫なの
This one here is a cat!
こいつは猫だ
No, that’s just her favorite line—
これはこの子の口…
Can’t we just call her a cat?!
もう猫でいいんだろう
本人が言ってるんだからいいの
She said it herself, so leave it!
All right!
はい
I. Am. A. Cat!
猫なの
Right! I will escort you to the exit!
おし　出口までご案内
Good-bye!
さようなら
Presently, the data is very complicated.
今　情報がかなり錯綜したのですが
Hey! Are you all ri—?
おい　大丈…
The weird thing fell.
変なの落ちてた
Um, is there any way I can help—
あの　何かお手伝いを…
頼むから　帰ってくれ
I’m begging you, please. Just go!
How is it? Can it be fixed?
どうだ　直るか
It’s already—
これもう…
Thank you, Rikuo-kun. But …
ありがとう　リクオ君
でも
After all that, let’s have a good chat.
せっかくだから　楽しくお話しましょう
じゃずっとその家で働いてたんだ
So, you’ve always been working at that house?
Yes. That was where I worked.
はい
そこが私の仕事場でした
I was tasked with looking after the son.
私はご子息の世話係として雇われましたが
But now, he has grown to a stage where I’m no longer needed.
今はもう私を必要としないほど成長されました
That job—did you like it?
その仕事好きだった?
Yes.
はい
The son bestowed a name upon me.
ご子息が私に名前をくださったのを
Even now, I remember it well.
今でもよく覚えています
大切な名前です
It’s an important name.
That child’s name! What was his name?
その子の名前　名前なんていうの
The son was …
ご子息は
「…」という名前です
His name was ✲✲✲✲.
What about the family name?
家族の名字は?
Their address? Contact details?
住所　連絡先は?
You were …
お前…
As I thought.
やっぱり…
I’m grateful that you asked about my name.
名前を聞いてくれて感謝します
“Everyone who comes here is the same.”
「ここに来る人はみんな同じ」
You called me,
あなたが私を呼んだのですね
didn’t you?
… Name … don’t … forget it …
名前を…忘れ…ないで
Yes! It is a drawing of Katoran!
そうだよ　カトランの絵だよ
Is it broken?
壊れたのか
It was illegally abandoned.
不法投棄されたんだ
は?
When a new android is purchased,
the old one should be returned to the maker.
新しいの買ったら　古いのはメーカーに回収してもらうだろう
At that time …
その時に
The collection fee.
回収費用
Because they didn’t want to pay it,
they erased their personal information.
払いたくないから　個人情報を消去して
This child, you see, wanted someone to remember him—
この子はね　誰かに覚えていてもらいたかったんだ
His own name.
自分の名前を
That’s why he has been evading the Ethics Committee.
だから　倫理委員会から逃げ続けて
You don’t know that.
分かんねぇだろう
It didn’t even know its own name.
名前なんて分かんなかっただろう
That was likely erased as well.
多分そこも消されて
That’s just like a robot, isn’t it?
ロボットらしいじゃねぇか
Not realizing that it had lost something ages ago.
とっくに無くしてんのにそれに気づきもしねぇで
They remained in this child’s heart the whole time;
この子の心の中にはずっとあったの
those precious memories of receiving his name.
名前をもらったときの大切な思い出
Heart? What do you mean by “heart”?
心?
心ってなんだよ
Masaki.
マサキ
You often said so yourself, didn’t you?
お前もよく言ってたじゃねぇか
“Because it doesn’t have a heart, it doesn’t understand music.”
「心がないから音楽も理解できない」って
How long are you going to stay there blubbering?
いつまでも浸ってんじゃねぇよ
Stop it already!
いい加減にしろ
What? Isn’t it strange?
んだよ
おかしいだろう
Right?
な
You too?
お前もかよ
Vagrant Robot
Report Form
So they also dispose of vagrant robots—
浮浪ロボットの処理もやってるんだ
The Ethics Committee.
倫理委員会って
That doesn’t mean I was involved.
俺がやってるわけじゃねぇよ
She’s really ignoring us huh.
やっぱり無視か
Isn’t that normal?
これが普通だろう
Sammy is like that at home too.
サミィも家じゃあんな感じ
Why is it different only at that café?
なんであの店だけ違うんだろう
Affection is not something they have.
思い入れなんて持つもんじゃねぇよ
This is me?
私…ですか
That’s right! It is a drawing of Katoran!
そうだよ　カトランの絵だよ
In a Time of Tenderness
Next up, the front page of Bankei News.
次はこちら　蟠渓新聞一面です
Android job types expand!
アンドロイドの業種拡大
It’s big news!
大きいですね
Where’s Sammy?
サミィは
It made that and went out a while ago.
とっくに出ていったそれ作って
Maintenance?
あっ　メンテか
月一とか面倒すぎ
So annoying. Once every month.
あれってどこ行ってんの　電気屋さん?
Where did it go?
An appliance shop?
Who knows.
さぁ　お父さんとこじゃないの
Probably Dad’s place.
眠い　食べたくない
I’m sleepy and don’t feel like eating.
Android job types expand.
Androids employed as school teachers?
Birth of android artists?
The piano.
ピアノ
What?
はい?
If you’re gonna play at night, turn off the sound!
夜中に弾くなら音消してよ
I’m losing sleep because of it.
こっちまで寝不足だわ
So it wasn’t a dream.
あれ…夢じゃない
Mom was heartbroken!
Gone for voice training
lessons. Sammy-chan,
take care of breakfast.
—Mom
お母さん嘆いてたよ
レッスンもう手伝ってもらえないって
Says she can’t have you help with the lessons.
Even if I were good at it, what’s the use?
僕がうまくなってもしょうがないじゃん
Hayama Junior Piano Competition
Robot gives guest performance.
Grand Prix – Sakisaka Rikuo (14 years old)
It doesn’t have any special abilities?
なんかこいつ特技とかねぇのかな
Special abilities in an android?
アンドロイドに特技とか
親父のPCん中で見つけた
I found this on my old man’s pc.
Uh …
えーと
It’s an android.
アンドロイドだ
人間の親になるためのな
Made to be a human being’s father.
I’ve heard about it—
こんなの聞いたこと…
They’re not actually in use.
実際に出回ってるわけじゃねぇ
They might be, in future.
将来的には実現したいって話だ
Read this.
ここを読んでみろ
… Operational tests conducted in secret …
Sounds familiar?
心当たりあるよな
Not particularly.
別に
It doesn’t mean he’s like that.
あの人がそうと決まったわけじゃ
It’s like robots are butting into everything.
ったく 何でもかんでもロボットが割り込んできやがって
First it’s art. Next it’ll be love!
芸術の次は愛情だな
Masaki!
マサキ
Would you eat a tomato created by machines?
Welcome!
いらっしゃい
You’re alone today?
今日は一人?
Not like we’re always together.
別にいつも一緒じゃ
You are!
一緒でしょう
そっちも一人?
She’s alone too?
うん
Shimei-san has something to take care of.
シメイさん　ちょっと用事で
So you handle child care too?
託児所もやってるんだ
Chie-chan is a customer!
チエちゃんはお客様
Right?
ね?
ニャー
What’s he up to?
何してるの　チエちゃん一人にして
Leaving Chie-chan on her own.
I’m a cat!
猫だもん
Don’t say things like that!
もうそんなこと言わないの
Sure, sure.
はいはい
Hopefully your dad will be back soon.
お父さん早く帰ってくるといいね
He’s not my dad!
お父さんじゃないもん
じゃ何
So who is he?
He’s called my … fos-ter-par-ent!
養育…里親っていうの
I’m back, Chie-chan!
戻ってきたよ　チエちゃん
I’m a cat!
猫なの
Oh. Rikuo-kun!
ああ　リクオ君
Huh? Where’s Masa-kun?
あれ　マサキ君は
It’s not like we’re always together!
だからいつも一緒じゃ
Sure you are!
一緒でしょう
You seem kind of out of it.
なんか元気ないね
Out of it, nyaa.
元気ないニャー
You’re wrong!
んなことないって
Chie-chan. Let’s read a book!
チエちゃん　ご本読もうか
I don’t feel like it.
いいもん読まなくて
シメイお爺ちゃんが好きな本知ってる
You know which book Shimei-ojiichan likes?
How about I show you?
教えてあげようか
ニャー
She’s good with kids.
うまいんだ子供の相手
That’s because she’s mature.
大人だからねアキコは
Unlike me.
私と違って
What does Shimei-san do for a living?
シメイさんって何してる人
I’m not sure what he does either.
私も知らないの
Except for doting on Chie-chan.
チエちゃんを溺愛してる以外はね
He should have taken her with him.
一緒に連れていけばいいのに
Probably.
多分　つらいのはシメイさんのほう
But Shimei-san’s the one who is suffering.
I kind of understand.
なんとなく分かるの
I’ve taken care of her many times.
もう何度も預かってるから
Many times?
何度も？
Right. Every month.
うん
毎月ね
Cats study too!
猫も勉強するもん
Are you okay?
大丈夫
I didn’t get enough sleep.
ちょっと寝不足
That’s not what I mean.
そうじゃなくて
Seems like you’re in a bad mood.
なんか不機嫌そう
どうせ僕は嫌な奴だよ
What does it matter?
You all hate me anyway!
What do you mean by that?
何よそれ
They say there’s nothing in your heart at birth.
生まれたばっかりだと　心の中は何にもないんだって
It’s empty.
空っぽ
Cats too?
猫も?
That’s right. But you talk with lots of people,
うん　でもねいろんな人と話して
いろんなものを見て感じてそうすると
and feel and see lots of things,
and gradually your heart comes into being.
だんだん心ができてくるんだって
Cats too?
猫にも
That’s right, but you’re still a child.
そうだよ　でもまだまだ
You’re going to experience many more emotions.
これからもっといろんな心ができてくるんだって
ニャー
Not just Chie-chan.
チエちゃんだけじゃなくて
Shimei-san, us, and also—
シメイさんも　僕たちも　それから
Rikuo-san?
リクオさん
This cat understands.
猫分かったよ
Really?!
本当
ニャー
Chie-chan understood before I did!
チエちゃんに先を越されちゃった
Are you lonely without Shimei-san?
シメイさんがいないと寂しい?
Do you like Shimei-san?
シメイさんのこと好き?
ニャー
Shimei-san went off somewhere, all on his own.
シメイさんって　一人でどこかに行っちゃうんだよね
I wonder where he goes,
どこ行ってるんだろうね　寂しがってるのに
and whether he’s lonely …
Rikuo-kun!
リクオ君
She’s just a child, you know?
大人気ないんだから
Um. Sorry.
ごめん
あのね　トイレ
Bathroom.
It’s Chie-chan’s turn now!
はい　今度はチエちゃんの番ね
リクオ君ちょっとごめんね
Rikuo-kun, excuse us a second.
Sure.
うん
本当は一人で行けるのに
I can do it by myself.
さすがチエちゃん
That’s my Chie-chan!
シメイ氏がこの店に初めてあの子を連れてきてから　もうかなりなる
Shimei-shi first brought her to this café quite some time ago.
According to that elderly gentleman,
あのご老人が言うには
she really likes it here.
ここは彼女のお気に入りなんだそうだ
I didn’t mean to weigh her down.
いじめるつもりはなかったんです
But something bothers—
でも　ちょっと気になることが…
It can’t be helped.
なに仕方ないさ
All human beings hurt their companions sometimes.
人間誰だって相手を傷つけることはある
What are you getting at?
どういう意味ですか
I guess that got you angry.
気に障ったかな
You’re saying I’m a bad guy because I’m a human?
僕が人間だから　嫌なやつだってことですか
You say some interesting things.
面白いことを言うな君は
Do you think robots never hurt others?
ロボットなら絶対に相手を傷つけないとでも
What is it that hurts others?
何が相手を傷つけるのか
It’s not such an easy thing to figure out.
そう簡単に分かることじゃない
What were your thoughts at that time?
その時どう考える
How can you avoid hurting others?
どうすれば傷つけずに済むか
What do you need to understand?
何を理解すればいいのか
It’s easy enough to say,
言葉にすれば
but quite another thing to put into action.
身も蓋もない話だな
Rikuo-san!
リクオさん
You saved me.
私はリクオさんに救われました
Is that so?
そうなんだ
Ughh, this sucks.
最悪だ
So you’re going into administrative justice.
じゃ司法関係に進むんだ
Seems not many lawyers specialize in robot law.
ロボット法の専門弁護士ってまだ少ないらしいし
But it’s still tough to get into.
まぁ狭き門には変わりねぇけどさ
What about you?
お前は
This, after all?
やっぱこれか
I’m quitting.
もうやめる
Why?
なんでだよ
Because of that, the other day?
やっぱあれかこの間の
うん
Forget about that.
別に気にすることはねぇって
Sure, it can play with precision.
そりゃ 正確には弾けんだろうけど
But it only stole a bit of the spotlight.
It was really … good.
すごく…うまかった
感動したかも
I was moved, I think.
By this?
これにか
Huh?
あれ
下手だな
It’s lousy.
Ah. That’s right!
そうか
I’m sorry.
ごめんなさい
I lied when I said I could play.
弾けるって言ったのは嘘
But you made it to the end, right?
一応最後まで弾けたのかな
本当は見様見真似なんです
Really. I just picked it up by watching.
I’d just heard it so many times. That’s all.
前に何度か聞いたことがあるだけで
チエちゃんがもっと聞きたいって
Play some more, play, play! Nyaa!
もっと弾いて
弾いて弾いて
ニャー
Chie-chan, what did you like best?
チエちゃんどんなところが気に入ったの
When it was … all broken up!
猫はね
えーとバラバラのとこ
バラバラ
バラバラですね
ねあれ見て
Look at that! Isn’t it amazing?
すごくない
Hey, Rikuo-kun.
ねリクオ君
Thanks for this.
これ　ありがとう
That’s not what you were playing before!
さっきのとは違うよ
Ma—
マ…
Rikuo-san!
リクオさん
Um, I’m …
あの…私
That piece you used to play;
昔リクオさんが弾いてたのを
I liked it.
その…好きで
And Chie-chan said she wanted to hear it.
そしたらチエちゃんが聞きたいって
でも　ちゃんと弾いたことなくて
But I’ve never really played it.
But she still enjoyed listening to it.
それでも　楽しそうに聞いてくれるから
I’m sorry for having been so inconsiderate.
勝手なことして　ごめんなさい
I tried not to play in front of you.
お前の前では弾かないようにしてた
And before I knew it, I’d stopped playing.
気が付いたら弾かなくなってた
お前までピアノうまくなったら嫌だし
I’d have hated it if even you could play well.
リクオさん
Rikuo-san.
But …
でも
… To hell with all that!
そんなのどうでもいいか
ニャー　ニャー　ニャー　ニャー
I want to hear more!
チエもっと聞きたい
Sammy might play for you!
サミィちゃんが弾いてくれるかもよ
ニャー
I’m so glad.
いや嬉しい
She hasn’t been that happy for a long time.
あの子があんなに喜んだのは本当に久しぶりです
It was no big deal.
僕は別に
As for me,
それに引き換え
I left her on her own again.
私はまたあの子を一人にしてしまいました
You can’t take her with you?
連れていけないんですか
I don’t want to show her yet.
まだあの子には見せたくないんです
Shimei, could it be that you’re—?
シメイさん　もしかしてあなたは
I am needed by her.
私はあの子に必要とされています
So I devote myself to her.
だから私はあの子のために尽くします
She is everything to me.
あの子は私のすべて
My only wish is to make her happy.
私の願いはただあの子を幸せにすることなんです
Just like your performance.
あなたの演奏のように
That’s why I was so happy.
だから嬉しかった
These feelings are genuine.
この気持ちは本物ですよ
あなたの演奏に感動した私に誓って
I was truly moved by your performance, I swear.
Is it okay to say that kind of thing?
言っていいんですかそんなこと
Just don’t tell Nagi-san.
ナギさんには内緒です
サミィちゃん見なかった?
Have you seen Sammy-chan?
Come to think of it,
そう言えば　私が来たときに入れ違いで出ていったような気がしますが
I think she left when I came in.
帰っちゃったんだ…
She left …
For your hard work.
お疲れ様
About Sammy;
サミィって
What?
なに
She makes a lot of friends.
いろんな関係作ってるんだなって
I-It’s not l-like I’m angry!
別に怒ってないよ
You were really cool.
格好良かった
This café—
この店
I … don’t hate it.
僕
嫌いじゃないよ
Thank you.
ありがとう
Rikuo-kun!
リクオ君
Right. I’ll explain it at the next meeting.
そうだ
その件は次の報告会で説明するつもりだ
I’m home.
ただいま
Anyway, take a look at the records.
とにかく　調書に目を通してくれ
Regardless of what the upper echelon say,
上の連中がなんと言おうと
this is the best way to study them all.
すべての会所を簡易調査するには　この方法がベストなはずだ
Where’s Dad?
お父さんは
He went to the Family Court.
家庭裁判所に出かけています
He is expected to be home shortly.
予定では　そろそろご帰宅されるはずです
絶対　お母さん悪くないよ
There’s no way Mom did anything wrong.
そうですね
That’s true.
But you can’t just blame Dad.
でも　お父さんだけを責めてはいけませんよ
Because neither side is clearly wrong.
どちらか一方が完全に悪いわけではないのですから
でも
But …
I have a favor to ask of you.
私からのお願いです
Sure!
はい
Let’s not tell Dad about this conversation.
この話はお父さんには内緒にしましょう
Why?
なんで
Because it would hurt Dad.
お父さんが傷つくからです
You don’t want that, right?
それは嫌でしょう
So I ask this favor of you.
では　私からのお願いです
Sure!
はい
Masakazu, there’s a problem.
困ったよ　マサカズ
I think it’s broken.
壊れてしまったのかな
Good morning, Tex.
おはよう　テックス
Tex.
テックス
Hey, Tex!
ね テックス
Tex!
テックス　テックス
Next, the report from the preliminary investigation.
続いて　事前調査の結果報告です
This shows the places that seem to be inciting excessive human–robot interactions.
アンドロイドと人間の過度な関係を誘発していると思われる施設の所在地を表示します
There’re too many.
多すぎるな
1408 places.
1408ヶ所です
We gathered all possible information and digitized it,
あらゆる情報を収集し　すべてデータ化しました
Baseless rumors and urban legends were included as well.
根拠のない噂話や都市伝説程度のものも含まれていると思われます
We need to narrow it down.
Time of Eve
もう少し絞るべきだな
Unfortunately, not all these places clearly violate robot law.
残念なことに　これらの施設がはっきりとロボット法に抵触しているとは限りません
They’re in the grey zone.
グレーゾーンです
That so many such places exist shows the limitations of robot law as it stands now.
そして対象がこれだけの数に上るという事実が
今のロボット法の限界でもあります
But these places must be eliminated.
だが　消し去るべき場所だ
We’ll do a cursory inspection of all the places,
これらの施設すべてに簡易調査を行い
and then pick targets for full investigation.
その結果次第で本調査の対象へと格上げします
メディアで吊るし上げるのはそれからです
After that, hand them over to the media.
But it’s impossible given the sheer number!
だからこの数では到底不可能だと言ってるんだ
That’s true, if you look at it only in terms of our manpower.
人材という観点から考えればそうですが
For the first time ever, we’ll use androids in the cursory investigation.
今回は初めて
簡易調査にアンドロイドを使用します
We’ve already secured a large number.
すでに相当数の機体を確保
We’re getting them ready now.
ただいま準備中です
What happened to your robot allergy?
ロボットアレルギーの君らしくないじゃないか
毒を以て毒を制す
We’re fighting poison with poison.
Please think of it that way.
と考えていただければよろしいかと
Continue.
続きを
はい
We’ll only investigate the places fully if accusations are supported by the android investigations.
このアンドロイドを使用した簡易調査で　裏づけが取れた案件のみを本調査リストに加えます
We’ll also record all androids and humans seen at each place, and follow up with more investigations.
更に その際現場で目撃した人間　アンドロイドすべてを記録
追跡調査を実施します　悪質な場合は　即座に警察当局内部のメンバーに通報　検挙を促します
Suspects will be reported to committee members in the police force, who will be urged to make arrests.
How are things with the apc?
APCの動向は
We were informed that someone found out about our preliminary investigations.
事前調査を嗅ぎまわっていた人物がいるとの情報が入っています
Their relationship with the apc is unclear.
APCとの関係性は不明
Also, lobbying has been diminishing.
また　ロビー活動はこのところ沈静化している模様です
Don’t forget that some parties will try to trip us up using this investigation.
聞いての通り　この調査に託けて
揚げ足を取ろうとする連中がいることを忘れないでいただきたい
We will issue absolute orders to the android investigators;
they must keep their ties with our committee a secret.
アンドロイド調査員には
本調査と倫理委員会の関係を極秘事項にするよう絶対命令を徹底します
Memories of that incident are fading.
あの傷害事件の記憶が風化している今
We must not make the same mistake again.
同じ過ちは決して犯してはならん
Carry on.
続けてくれ
I’m from the media strategy division.
メディア戦略部です
About cio Masaki’s tv appearance—
真崎CIOのテレビ出演が一件
うちの家内が欠かさずアーカイブしててな
My wife records them all.
Drives me nuts!
敵わんよ
これは強調しておきますが
I’d like to emphasize that our Ethics Committee is raising the alarm about robots infiltrating daily life. That’s all.
われわれ倫理委員会が警鐘を鳴らしているのは　あくまで日常生活の場に進出するロボットの存在です
Woah! What a lady-killer!
おお　マダムキラーって感じ
Huh? In what way?
えっどの辺
Hey! You changed the channel!
ああ　勝手に弄ってる
Don’t mind it!
お邪魔してます
Children treat robots like people no matter how primitive the robots are.
primitive they are.　特に子供は それが原始的な造形のロボットであっても　擬人化してしまえるんですよ
それによって本来あるべきはずの人間同士の関係性が阻害される
And that impedes the fostering of inter-personal relationships humans should have.
One Evlend!
イヴレンド
It’s an encroachment on human dignity.
人間の尊厳が侵されている
Sure.
はい
The issue I’m raising here is—
ここで問題にしたいのは
Hey, why doesn’t Masaki-kun come anymore?
ねね　最近来ないね真崎君　なんで
Actually, a lot has happened.
実は色々あって
A lot?!
色々って
Well. The biggest reason is …
まぁ一番の原因は
This guy is on tv a lot these days, huh?
最近この顔よく見ない
Yeah. Like the old days.
まぁね
昔みたい
What was that?
何それ
The parent organization of the Robot Ethics Committee …
倫理委員会の母体となる組織は　ロボットが一般家庭に普及し始めた当初から存在していた
has been around since androids started being used in households.
That’s more than ten years ago.
もう十年以上前か
I heard that it started out as a radical anti-robot organization.
当時はかなり過激なロボット排斥団体だったと聞いている
I had no idea.
全然知らなかった
ここ数年鳴りを潜めていたからな
They’ve been quiet for the past few years.
What do you mean?
どういうことですか
Their extremism led to an incident.
昔　その過激さゆえに傷害事件を起こしたことがあってね
The Tokisaka Incident, right?
それって　トキサカ事件のことですよね
I’ve heard of it.
聞いたことあります
Ah. They say it was an accident.
まぁ事故とも言われているが
At any rate, they were severely censured, and the head resigned.
いずれにせよ　世間からの非難は必至　責任取って当時の会長は辞任
Since then, they’ve been quiet, at least until recently.
それ以来少なくとも最近までは大人しかった　というわけだ
You’ve lost me.
難しい話
Does it have anything to do with Masaki-kun?
それが真崎君と関係あんの
… that is our stance.
…そう考えております
真崎様　ありがとうございました
Thank you very much.
Today’s guest for Zoom-in
Scramble was Masaki Atsuro,
本日のズームインスクランブルはゲストに倫理委員会広報官
真崎篤郎様をお迎えし　お話し伺いました
Chief Information Officer of the Ethics Committee.
Masaki.
真崎
That’s right. His family circumstances …
うん　家庭の事情かな
I invited him today, too—
今日も誘ったんだけど
真崎って名字だったの
So Masaki is his last name.
You’re hung up on that?
そっちですか
Not that!
そっちじゃない
Father’s orders?
Speakers could be broken!!!
So, how’s it going?
よ　元気か
There’s this café called Time of Eve.
イヴの時間って店があってさ
Rikuo’s a big fan.
リクオがご執心なんだよ
Well. I go there too, so who am I to talk?
まぁ俺も行ってるから　人のこと言えねぇけどさ
人間とアンドロイドが普通に話すんだぜ
Humans and androids talk to each other!
It’s totally absurd.
バカみたいなとこだろう
Right?
なぁ
Say something.
なんか言えよ
I’m coming in.
入るぞ
Who’re you talking to?
誰と話してるんだ
My mobile phone.
携帯
I hung up already.
もう切った
コーヒーを入れさせたのか
You had it make coffee?
うん
You’re at home a lot these days.
最近家にいることが多いじゃないか
Did something happen?
何かあったのか
何でも父さんに言いなさい
You can tell me anything.
There’s nothing.
いや 別にないけど
そうか
I see.
Don’t trust robots too much when it comes to things you eat and drink.
口に入れるものはあまりロボット任せにするなよ
Thx. We’ll write up the minutes for today’s meeting tonight.
THX 今夜中に今日の報告会の議事録を作成しろ
The data is in my terminal.
データは私の端末の中だ
Tell Masaki-kun he’s welcome any time.
いつでも来てって言ってね真崎君に
Sure, I’ll tell him.
うん　言っとく
But don’t get your hopes up.
あんまり期待しないでほしいけど
See you.
それじゃ
バイバイ
Come again!
また来てね
Um. He’s gone.
あの　帰りましたけど
You know, I don’t think Rikuo-kun minds anymore.
ねぇ　リクオ君も気にしてないと思うけど
私はそんな感じするよ
That’s the impression I get.
Nagi-san, you don’t understand Rikuo.
ナギさんはリクオのこと分かってないの
I’ve known him longer.
私の方が付き合い長いんだから
I’m sure he doesn’t want to see me here yet.
きっとまだ顔を合わせたくないって思ってる
Really?
そう?
Hey, who cares about Rikuo-kun?
ねぇ　リクオ君のことはどうでもいいんだけどさ
Don’t say that!
I can’t just ignore him!
どうでもいいことないでしょう
そういう言い方しないでよ
Oh? So that’s how it is.
そうなんだ
Don’t go telling Rikuo-kun strange things.
リクオ君に変なこと吹き込まないでね
バイバイ
Masaki-kun’s not going to report this place, is he?
真崎君　告げ口したりしないよね
ニャー
If that happens, this café will have to close.
その時は　クローズするしかないわねこの店
No! … Even though it’s such a wonderful place?
そんな　素敵な場所なのに
Sammy-chan.
サミィちゃん
Do you remember how you first came here?
最初にどうやってここに来たのか覚えてる
I thought you called me.
ナギさんが呼んでくれたのかと思った
I’m not able to bring anyone here.
私には誰も連れてくることなんてできない
You probably learned about Time
of
Eve from someone who’d been here.
あなたにイヴの時間を教えたのは　多分ここに来たことのある誰か
And Sammy-chan, you brought Rikuo-kun and Masaki-kun.
そして そんなサミィちゃんがリクオ君と真崎君を連れてきた
So if Masaki-kun brings someone from the Ethics Committee,
だからね　真崎君が連れてくるのが倫理委員会の人なら　それはそれで仕方のないこと
there’s nothing we can do about it.
That’s the end of these connections.
この繋がりはそこでお仕舞い
And the end of this café.
この店もお仕舞い
Nagi-san, are you okay with that?
ナギさんはそれでいいの
ここはね　みんなの心一つで成り立つお店
In this café, everyone’s hearts come together as one.
I just want to see it through.
私は見届けたいだけ
How big can this circle grow?
この輪がどこまで広がっていけるのか
Um. Master.
あの　マスター
Wh-what?
な…なに
Would you like Masaki-sama to come again?
真崎様にまた来てほしいですか
To Time of Eve.
イヴの時間に
Yes. I’d like him to come again.
うん　来てほしいと思ってる
I would like that too.
私もそう思います
Okay! I’ll definitely bring him tomorrow!
よし　明日こそ絶対に連れていくぞ
Masaki!
マサキ
今日は…
Today—
I’m not going.
行かねぇよ
She said she wants you to come again.
また来てほしいって言ってたよ
Don’t just say things.
適当なこと言うな
It’s true!
本当だって
Who?
誰がだよ
えーとナギさんとか
Nagi-san, and—
Sammy said so too!
あっ サミィも言ってた
She said she wants you to come too.
あいつも来てほしいって
They want me to come?
来てほしいって
So what? It’s a houseroid!
なんだよ
ハウスロイドだぜ
うん
That’s right.
そうだよ
お前
You’ve … changed.
変わったよな
Masaki, what’s going on?
マサキ
ね　なんだよ
You’re just like I was, back then.
あの頃の俺と同じじゃねぇのか
You’ll feel affection, only to be betrayed later.
愛情を感じたって　いつか裏切られる
It’d be better if that café didn’t exist.
あんな店ない方がいいだろう
That’s right. It’d be better if it didn’t exist.
そうだ
ない方がいい
Dad! I want to talk to you about something!
親父　話があるんだ
Thx is gone.
THXがいなくなった
Masakazu, did you give it an order?
マサカズ　何か命令したのか
No.
いや
It just went off.
勝手にいなくなるなんて
It’s completely broken.
完全にいかれたか
速いところ見つけて処分しないとな
Gotta find it right away, and get rid of it.
Get rid of it?
処分
Of course!
当たり前だ
It’s handled lots of Ethics Committee material.
あれは倫理委員会の資料にも散々触れているんだぞ
Gotta take care of it before it becomes a headache!
面倒なことになる前になんとかするんだ
Masaki. I’m at Time of Eve. Can you help me?
マサキ　今はイヴの時間なんだけど
ちょっと助けてくれない
What’s that sound?
なんだよこの音
An ancient robot—uh, an elderly customer—is here.
やたら旧式のロボット…あっ
古い感じのお客が来てるんだけど
It says to close the café!
この店を閉鎖しろって
I’m asking, what is that sound?
だから音はなんだって
The screen …
これは…
とにかく何言っても止めないんだ
Anyway, it won’t stop, whatever we say!
And this thx model won’t talk.
それにこのTHX型全然しゃべらないし
Hey—what did you just say?
おい　なんだって
This café falls under the grey zone, right?
この店ってグレーゾーンなんでしょう
Do something with those robot laws of yours, please?
こっちに来てお得意のロボット法でなんとかしてくれないかな　なんて
That was fast!
速っ
Close this establishment immediately.
Tex, stop it.
テックス　止めろ
T-Tex?
テ…テックス
What are you doing here?
お前なんでここに
Oh, so that’s what this is about?
そういうことか
You bring someone’s robot, and you want to make a scene, huh?
人んちのロボットを勝手に連れてきて　三文芝居でも見せようってかお前らは
I don’t know how you brought it here,
どうやって連れてきたのか知らねぇけどさ
but you people got Rikuo’s robot to come here.
まぁあれだろう　リクオのロボットも連れてきたくらいだ
You can do all kinds of things.
色々とできんだろう
This is a strange place, after all.
この不思議なお店はよ
Nagi-chan didn’t bring it here.
べ…別にナギちゃんが連れてきたんじゃ
Aki-chan.
アキちゃん
You’ll go that far to get me to come here.
そこまでして俺を引っ張り出したいわけだ
I’ll tell you my story.
教えてやるよ
It raised me, long ago.
昔こいつに育てられた
It was my best friend.
誰よりも仲がよかったな
Then one day, it suddenly stopped talking.
ある時こいつは突然しゃべらなくなった
I was a kid, and thought it was family. I felt hurt and betrayed.
ガキだった俺は　家族と思ってたこいつに裏切られて傷ついたわけだ
That’s it. No big deal.
以上
大した話しじゃない
There must be a reason it didn’t talk.
しゃべらないのはきっと理由があるんじゃないかな
I agree.
私もそう思います
It doesn’t look so broken down.
彼はそこまで壊れている状態には見えません
I know.
分かってるよ
I was only four or five years old,
四五年もすりゃ　俺もガキなりに察しがつくようになったさ
but I could guess what was going on.
My dad ordered it to stop talking.
親父が命令したんだ
Told it not to talk under any circumstance.
何があってもしゃべるなってな
He tried to drive us apart.
俺とこいつを引き離そうとしたんだろう
Just like something my dad would do.
親父のやりそうなこった
Orders from parents get priority.
親の命令は優先される
Masaki-kun, you’re very perceptive.
真崎君は聡明でらっしゃる
“Perceptive”?
聡明って
I didn’t know that when I was a kid!
ガキの頃は分かんなかったんだよ
I kept trying to talk with it!
こいつとまた話すためなら何でもした
I even cried and apologized!
泣いて謝ったこともあんだぜ俺は
If commanded, it can ignore a crying, wailing child.
命令されりゃ　泣き喚く子供だって無視できんだよ
For years.
何年もな
Ultimately,
結局
they can’t understand people’s hearts!
こいつらは人の心なんて分かりやしないんだ
簡易調査にアンドロイドを使用します
“… use androids in the cursory investigation.”
“This café called Time of Eve … I go there too …”
イヴの時間って店があってさ
俺も行ってるから　人のこと言えねぇけどさ
“Record all androids and humans … urge arrests.”
現場で目撃した人間　アンドロイドすべてを記録
検挙を促します
“… should be eliminated.”
消し去るべき場所だ
I am going to br-break th-this café’s rule.
今から　こ…この店のルールをや…破ります
You are in violation of Robot Law 9, Article 3.
あなたはロボット法第九条第三項に抵触しています
According to data in my possession, you are an android.
なぜなら私の保持するデータによると　あなたはアンドロイドであり
If an android deactivates its ring while still active,
アンドロイドが起動中にリングを消すのは
it is in violation of robot law.
ロボット法違反に当たるからです
What’s going on?
なんだよこれ
Why is Tex speaking?
なんでテックスがしゃべってんだよ
What about Dad’s command?
親父の命令はどうなってんだ
A command.
命令
It’s breaking a command.
命令を破る
Breaking the Second Law …
第二条を破る
… is permitted only in upholding the First Law.
第二条を破れるのは第一条だけ
The First Law means … danger?
第一条　危険
A human here is in danger?
誰が
人間が
この場にいる人間が危険
Can’t be. Who does Tex know to be human?
いや　テックスが人間だと分かるのはこの場では俺だけ
Only I.
俺が危険
I’m in danger?
だから俺を守るために
Tex is speaking … to protect me?
しゃべる
Hence, it is necessary to take legal action against your owner.
よって　あなたの管理者に対し法的措置を講じる必要があります
I require your owner’s information.
あなたの管理者の情報を求めます
“We will issue absolute orders to the android investigators; they must keep their ties with our committee a secret.”
本調査と倫理委員会の関係を極秘事項にするよう
絶対命令を徹底します
真崎君
Masaki!
マサキ
I’m not letting go!
放さねぇぞ
Unless you … unless you talk to me,
お前が　お前が俺にしゃべるまで放さねぇぞ
I’m not letting go!
Tell me!
教えてくれ
What were you thinking?
お前は何を思ってた
For so many years.
何年もずっと
All that time.
Watching me … all those years.
ずっと
ずっと俺を見てきて
俺の傍にいて
You were right there with me.
Tex, help me!
テックス　助けてくれ
Speak to me!
俺に声をかけてくれよ
I couldn’t speak to you.
話しかけることはできなくて
I always wanted to be at your side.
ずっと傍にいたくて
I …
私
私は
… always …
ずっと
Masakazu-kun—
マサカズ君のことを
He wanted to protect you.
この子　真崎君を守りたかったんじゃないかな
分かってるよんなこと
I know that much.
危険が去ったらしゃべれない
It won’t speak once the danger has passed.
It’s still bound by Dad’s command.
こいつはまだ親父の命令に縛られたままだ
You wanted me to understand too, huh?
お前も分かってほしかったのか
But, even so, I can’t accept this.
でもな　やっぱ納得できねぇよ
It might be impossible now,
今は無理かもしれないけど
but someday, surely, it will talk.
いつかきっとしゃべれるようになるよ
Don’t just say things.
適当なこと言うな
I didn’t.
違うんだ
It’s not like I don’t have a reason.
理由がないんじゃなくて
But I can’t express it well.
うまく言えないけど
I’ve seen so many things here.
ここでいろんなこと見てきて
There’re many problems.
問題は色々あるけど
It’s distressing to see them each time.
その都度悩んで
But this feels like the right path.
でも
進んでる方向は間違ってない気がするんだ
It’s the same for you, Masaki.
マサキもだって同じだよ
I’m sure.
だから　きっと
You might be right.
そうかもな
I’ll tell Dad that I brought you out of the house.
親父には俺が連れ出したことにしとくぞ
I … always … Masakazu-kun …
私は
ずっと
マサカズ君のことを
Let’s go home.
帰ろうぜ
How did it get in?
どうやって入ったんだ
I held it.
抱えて
I lifted it up.
持ち上げて
You really are demanding a lot!
ったく世話焼かせやがって
Someday I’ll get you to thank me for today.
いつか今日の礼を言わせてやるからな
I love everyone.
みんな大好き
I’m so happy we can all be here.
嬉しいの
ここにいることができて
They’re going home together!
一緒に帰ってるよ
It’s all right.
It’s all right.　いいの
Should I have helped them?
手助けするべきでしたか
No. It’s enough that you watched over them.
いえ　見届ければそれでいい
It might have developed into another dangerous incident.
また危険な事件に発展する可能性もありました
I’m sure Shiotsuki understands that much.
潮月ならそれくらい分かってるはず
But is this really related to Shiotsuki-shi?
そもそも本当に潮月氏と関係があるのですか
That café’s rule …
あの店のルール
Indeed, it was 1138.
確かに1138です
1138.
The Priority Order code that can even override our country’s robot laws.
我が国のロボット法すら上回る命令優先コード
That would make sense.
これで説明がつくはずよ
Code:life’s deterrent circuit isn’t working.
code:LIFEの抑制回路が機能しない
This is all to prepare for that time.
Time of Eve’s rule
In this café,
there is no discrimination
between humans and robots.
Customers, please cooperate.
Obey the rule and have a fun time…
すべてあの時間のために
Could anyone else but Shiotsuki have done it?
そんなことできる人間が潮月以外に
しかし
But—
One more thing.
もう一つ
Android control taken to new extremes
トキサカ事件　当時の記事ですか
An article about the Tokisaka
Incident, from when it happened?
No, this is …
いや　これは…
It’s the real article, before the contents were replaced.
配信間際で差し替えられた本当の記事
If this girl, five years old at the time, is by chance still alive …
当時五歳の少女
仮にまだ生きているとすれば
Time of Eve
Retain
I forgot to bring out your Evlend today.
今日はイヴレンド出しそびれちゃった
I thought something was missing.
なんか物足りないと思った
How did Tex get to the café?
テックスってどうやってこの店に来たんだろう
You don’t know?
あら分かんない?
You do?
知ってるの
I thought you were a regular here.
もうすっかり常連だと思ってたのに
Rikuo-kun, you’ve got a long way to go.
リクオ君もまだまだね
ま…まだまだですか
Still a long way?
Huh? Someone new?
新入りさん?
I’m going to say hello.
ちょっと挨拶してくるね
This is my tale of the Time of Eve.
これが僕のイヴの時間での物語り
Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ
Take any seat that’s free!
空いてる席にどうぞ
I’ll take your order soon.
注文取りに行くから
Many more things happened to me, but …
僕はこのあともここでいろんな体験をするんだけど
You might not be here for long, but enjoy yourself!
短い時間かもしれないけど　楽しんでってね
… that’s another story.
それはまた別のお話し
ko
u
e
n
no
be
n
chi
de
wa
ra
t
te
i
ta
We were laughing on the park bench
公園のベンチで笑っていた
kouen no benchi de waratteita
坐在公园的长椅上微笑
公園のベンチで笑っていた
na
tsu
no
a
sa
that summer morning
natsu no asa
夏日的清晨
夏の朝
夏の朝　草原が緑に輝いてた
so
u
ge
n
ga
mi
do
ri
ni
ka
ga
ya
i
te
ta
and the grass was shining green
sougen ga midori ni kagayaiteta
草地的绿色闪耀着光芒
草原が緑に輝いてた
ho
n
to
u
ga
mi
e
na
i
ki
mi
no
hi
to
mi
What color are your eyes
ほんとうは見えない君の瞳　どんな色
hontou wa mienai
无法看透你的双眸
ほんとうは見えない
kimi no hitomi donna iro
有着怎样的颜色
君の瞳どんな色
do
n
na
i
ro
that don't see the truth?
ki
mi
ga
te
ru
so
ra
o
mi
tsu
ke
ta
ku
te
I want to find the sky you see
君が見てる空を見つけたくて
kimi ga miteru sora wo mitsuketakute
想寻找你所仰望的那片天空
君が見てる空を見つけたくて
I
have
a
dream
I have a dream
sa
ya
ka
su
gi
te
A very modest one
sasayaka sugite totemo
非常渺小
ささやかすぎてとても
to
te
mo
ki
mi
ni
i
e
so
u
ni
wa
na
i
ke
re
do
Even if I can't tell you about it
kimi ni iesou ni wa nai keredo
无法对你说出口
君に言えそうにはない けれど
君に言えそうにはないけれど
a
sa
ga
ku
ru
me
o
ko
su
ri
Morning comes, rubbing my eyes
朝が来る　目をこすり
asa ga kuru me wo kosuri
清晨醒来 睡眼惺忪
朝が来る　目をこすり
hi
to
go
mi
o
a
ru
i
te
ku
I walk through the crowd
人混みを歩いてく
hitogomi wo aruiteku
踱步在人群中
人混みを歩いてく
ku
ri
ka
e
su
hi
bi
no
na
ka
in these repeating days
繰り返す日々の中
kurikaesu hibi no naka
在不断重复的日子里
繰り返す日々の中
chi
i
sa
na
yu
me
o
sa
ga
shi
tsu
zu
ke
ru
I keep searching for a little dream
小さな夢を探し続ける
chiisana yume wo sagashi tsudzukeru
不断追寻那小小的梦想
小さな夢を探し続ける
sol
te
i
mar
ti
a
ses
ta
i
mar
ti
a
kon
te
si
mi
a
to
i
si
ri
a
vi
to
mi
a
kon
te
i
mar
ti
a
ses
ta
i
mar
ti
a
kon
te
i
mi
a
sa
si
ri
a
do
che
i
vis
ta
to
ki
wa
yu
ku
bo
ta
chi
wa
su
re
chi
ga
i
ma
ta
de
a
u
Time goes by, we miss each other and meet again
時は行く　僕達は　すれ違い　また出会う
toki wa yuku bokutachi wa
时光流逝 我们
時は行く 僕達は
surechigai mata deau
擦身而过 又再次相遇
すれ違い　また出会う
ko
go
e
te
ta
fu
yu
no
hi
o
ka
mi
shi
me
te
reflecting upon the frozen day of winter
凍えてた冬の日をかみしめて
kogoeteta fuyu no hi wo kamishimete
细细品味严寒的冬日
凍えてた冬の日をかみしめて
a
sa
ga
ku
ru
ka
ze
ga
fu
ku
Morning comes, the wind is blowing
朝が来る　風が吹く
asa ga kuru kaze ga fuku
清晨来临 微风习习
朝が来る　風が吹く
hi
to
go
mi
o
a
ru
i
te
ku
I walk through the crowd
hitogomi wo aruiteku
踱步在人群中
人混みを歩いてく
ki
mi
no
ta
me
bo
ku
no
ta
me
for you, for me
君のため　僕のため
kimi no tame boku no tame
为了你 为了自己
君のため　僕のため
se
ka
i
wa
yu
me
o
tsu
mu
gi
tsu
zu
ke
ru
the world keeps spinning dreams
sekai wa yume wo tsumugi tsudzukeru
世界继续编制梦想
世界は夢を紡ぎ続ける
I’m back.
ただいま
Looks like things are fine.
まだ大丈夫そう
You’ve worked hard.
苦労かけるね
Though it doesn’t smell like salt,
塩の香りはしないけど
I still like the current café.
今の店も好きよ
It’s in the city, so lots of people gather there.
町だからいろんな子が集まるの
Is everyone doing well?
みんな元気かい
うん
悲しい顔してる
You look sad.
She …
あの子が
Ever since Ashimori broke her,
芦森に壊されてからずっと
不安なんだ
I’ve been feeling insecure.
They—
みんな
Will they find happiness?
幸せになれるのかな
No matter how many times we try …
何回試しても
This time round—how many times has it been now?
今度の場所　何度目だ?
Three times …
三度目
Or four …
四度目
They—
みんな
Will they be able to laugh?
笑えるようになるのか
I—
僕は
Your children are laughing …
あなたの子供たちは笑ってる
Alongside humans.
人間と一緒に
I feel insecure.
不安で
It’s unbearable.
たまらないんだ
It’s all right.
大丈夫
Someday, definitely, it will extend beyond the café.
いつかきっとお店だけじゃなくて
Something happened today to make me think that.
今日ねそう思えることがあったの
Won’t you tell me about it?
聞かせてくれないか
The main character is a certain boy.
主人公はある男の子
So today’s story is …
だから今日のお話はね